All rights.
Good afternoon everyone thank you for coming.
So, I hope everyone's having a great day one and build twenty fifteen
my name is charles morris and this is...and we're both pm leads on
the microsoft edge team is so great to be able to say that out loud.
we're here today to give you an introduction to microsoft edge new browser
the new web platform and the new foundation for web apps in windows ten.
just a quick reminder to please fill...evaluation after the session let us know what you think.
So, we have a lot to cover I think it's safe to say that this
is the biggest release for microsoft and the web for quite a long-time.
And, we have a lot
to cover luckily we have a lot of deep dive sessions to point you towards but,
in the interest of saving time I'm actually going to start right now by combining an agenda
and architecture slide together I don't think I've ever seen this done before it's pretty amazing so,
we're going to cover three main things the first thing is microsoft edge the browser
so...you through some of the design...through a tour of
features as well as some of the technical underpinnings for the browser.
I'm going to talk about microsoft edge html which is a new
rendering engine that power's microsoft edge so I'll talk about the new focus
for this engine as well as a bunch of...new features that are coming to this new web platform...
html in addition to powering microsoft edge is also powering
the new web out platform for windows ten so this is really a new approach
a web apps that that's really going to be more friendly to web developers so how
many of you out there build websites either for work or on your spare time?
So, quite a few if you how many of you use
web-based technology in an app that's distributed through store.
So, slightly smaller crowd how
many of you use a browser to surf the internet
okay sorry I need to get everyone to raise your hand at least one so,
if you raise your hand and then they'll be something here for you.
before getting into all of that I thought we should take a step back and really talk about context of why
this is such a big release and why microsoft decided to build a new browser
and new platform at this time?
But, more importantly then, you know, why we thought it was the right time I think it's important for us
to think about why you should care for both for yourself
as a developer as well as for your customers?
And, to understand this we really need to take
...journey back about a year-ago when we started planning windows ten.
...when we started planning windows ten we really started by saying we need to build
a stronger connection with our customers web developers browser
enthusiasts so we need to start investing in building feedback channels and just participating
in existing ones and we actually started a year-ago here build where
...status dot modern dot...in beta and what this is a lot of you're
probably familiar with it but what it is a public roadmap so is our way of starting tell
people here's what's in development here's what's under consideration so,
that everyone knows what we're working on a month later we launched in open-source the
site and since then we've been really updating and every month so people know exactly what we're working
on but it wasn't enough to just tell you what we're working on we also needed to let you tell us
what you thought so we added a little vote...there which
linked software user voice site where all of you hopefully some of you have exhausted all of your
twenty-five votes here to tell us what you want to see next in the web platform?
But, of course it's a lot it's about a lot more than features right we want to hear what you had
to say so we start to get really active on twitter and
we started holding these monthly ask ie sessions and for all of you speed readers you're seeing
the people really did ask us all sorts of things and we did our best to actually
answers honestly as we could.
And, since one hundred forty...is sometimes a little constraining we also did a reddit
ame which was a lot of fun.
But, beyond that we also want to broaden the reach of feedback beyond people who are on twitter
or reddit and get feedback from our broad-base of customers in the way we did this was
promoting the in product feedback so some of you notice that the smiley
face in windows ten moved up to the top-level you why here it is an
ie because it launched their first but of course...forward into microsoft edge
...what this allowed us to do is start to capture feedback really quickly from...
Again, who don't go to these other places within just a couple
cliques they can start to tell us when things are going wrong or not working the
way they expect and a little bit later on we'll start to see how we're using some of this data?
So, when we took a step back and looked at
all of that feedback that we were we were hearing we start to see a few key trends?
So, to understand that I thought we could look at kind of
...history of the web to talk about these three main things that we talk and we started to see.
The first one was that the technology underpinning the web has really evolved a
So, early on you can see the web spin around for
a over twenty five years as of last year...celebrated his twenty fifth anniversary
...older than some of you in the audience I'm not sure.
And,...has been around for most that time.
So, we had kind of the early portion of the web where things are crazy...like the wild west
...revolving really quickly lots new technologies lots
...versions ...in addition to new standards like html for
...css too because they were so many gap there's also a lot of proprietary technology so
you started to see things like active-x or vp script via
mel vector markup language starting to emerge that were not standards-based.
And, this of course culminated with a ie six which was kind of the dominant browser
of the time and at the time people kind of thought that
the web was maybe done like this we've checked that box we know-how to do the web.
But, it turns out that the web actually has a lot more impact
...that I think really what makes it unique is the enormous reach and diversity so the
way that the web gets to everyone regardless of the os device is
really by serving this enormous diversity of clients?
And, that really started to re-re emerge.
Through kind of this transition phase of the web...fire faq started
...up the competition again and with ie eight we really started to move back
...the standards-based approach.
And, then finally we've moved and
...last year's the pace of innovation is kind of pick back up with html five
so forth so the main message we heard here from our customers was okay things have
changed a lot we have we really want to move forward and leave a lot of these
ie proprietary technologies behind and yet we
also had these customers on the other end of the spectrum they said hey I have a site that needs active-x or
...phoebe script...just need those continue working in fact
whenever you upgrade it would be really great if you stop breaking that.
So, we had kind of this tension happening that we needed to deal with so that's the first thing we
heard.
The second thing we heard was,
you know,...really strong competitors emerging so fire
fox's I mentioned earlier safari especially on mobile and then
more recently chrome on the pc as well as mobile.
And, by providing a per powerful platform great market share and great user
experiences these are starting to really in some cases become quite dominant so
we started hearing from developers especially was hey we've seen this story before we need to make
sure we really need microsoft a competitive and making sure that the web
continues to thrive on the basis of having multiple
in independent implementations kind of this balance that's driving the web forward.
So, that was the second thing the third thing we heard was
apps so all of you probably see deal with this it's part of why you're here
so there was this emergence of the app store and all of the probably seen surveys where you're
seeing people spend less time and browsers and more time and apps and yet for a lot
of developers especially those that were used to the web there was some conflict
there cycle ki want to go where my users are going and I want to provide them with richer
experiences and yet I don't want to lose what's great about the web...love being able
to deploy and push updates like that I love to cross platform
nature of the web so that I don't have to rebuild things over and over again.
So, this was a third thing that we heard in really cause
us to rethink how we bring web apps into windows ten?
So, taken altogether this is really what caused us to
realize that we need to do more than...produce the next version of the browser we
...we needed...fundamental shifts in the way we do things and this is
what led to not just...browser with it, you know, and,
fresh coat of paint not just swapping out the engine not just a
new about platform but really all three of those things so without I'm going to handed off to...
Yeah, so, along with the changes in the web
and the web technology web standards the actual world around which the browsers
bills also been change of the last twenty years and we have been
...improving the browser over time but there's a very fundamental ways of things are changing
particularly windows ten some of those really take a step function complexity, for example,
we've moved from,... a single form factor ninety-five, you know,
pc mouse keyboard to multiple form factors mobile and pc and with windows
tenor actually...further with large-screen surface hub
x boxes multi-use with...and you saw spartan in the demo this morning is, you know,
stuck up against the wall
you interact with it with your in art your eye tracking in your finger and,
then small devices icy devices wearables things like that and we
have to think about what do we have a browser platform the way that we're building a browser the way that we
structuring the app they can actually allow us to scale across all of these different devices.
Also change expectations from users,
for example, this idea of a mobility of experience which is instead of
...a single device actually have multiple devices and I multiple devices the same time I
...able to move that experience from one
to the other I want to be able to have similar experiences on...to at the same time
...these expectation that in addition to having my experience device
...multiple devices.
...expectation that I'm always online or these I have connectivity to some form of
...whether it's a cellular network or wi-fi pretty much at all times across some kind of
a across various devices and that expectations sort of been going up-and-up and up-and-up
overtime in nineteen ninety five...launch forty five million people on the planet had
access the internet just last year we just crossed three billion people with access the internet so,
this huge sort of movement of people like they have...expectation of being
online having the internet be a part of their experience wherever they are.
And, the third sort of thing that people are expecting is the
...devices we smarter to be more personal in some cases have or personality
...kind of more interesting more engaged understand them and sort
...magically through the our of the...in most cases sort of figure out what
is they need and make their lives a little bit easier so people start have expectation about the product
...use...they're smart and their personal an environment around which the browser the...is also been changing
radically there's all these different kinds of input naturally user input speech touched
...tracking gestures things like that and these thinking about how does the browser
adapts into these different inputs is very important for us.
And, our consumption actually turns out we're really important thing as devices get smaller is battery's
get smaller as people are more mobile...amount of our that your product uses
that browser on the product uses a...very important application...uses is another
...that we have sort of think about up-front and these...questions we ask ourselves do we have
the right browser platform for these changing environments and finally...probably
not all lease security environment the privacy environment has changed radically and...
ramps up significantly I'm sure you don't spend more than a few days internet without finding out about
some...the new hack or some amount of data was lost or, you know,
the latest zero day on ...browser so, you know,
these this...environment which we live that the products that we build are being attacked on a regular basis
and...we approach the browser we looked at the product we had we sort of said, you know,
we need to go beyond sort of the code of panes and beyond simply changing the engine
...to rethink how're building the browser how're shipping it how we engineer and how
...approach sort of the problems that we think the browser needs to solve for the
...basic design tenants.
As we approach the first one first most important one...been amazing browser
...be secure with reliable we have...respect users privacy
...gap tabs you have to have printing and sharing and all...sort of basic things that people expect out of
a browser we have to be amazing at that anything else that we do on top of that
are beside that without actually landing the idea of having amazing browser
...of goes for not if people just can't do what they need to do...course...will
web just works for them as well as a charles talked about with respect to the platform the second thing
we said we're going to be bowls...forward-looking and that sort of meant as we'll talk about
...some of the things that we took for granted as we've been developing
sort and explore over the years and iterate...some of those things we took for granted like we had
to maintain support for certain types of extensibility, for example, we were going to take that
step function away because the environment in which we we're operating meant that those things
...keeping us from building the browser that was this a secures we
needed to be as fast as we needed to be and,
as reliable as we needed to be and the third thing and this is sort of aligns with the windows ten overall windows
a service is we decided we were going to ship fast trying new things and
...always get better so we started last year with, you know,
shipping developer previews as part of an underneath under ieee
...those features out there triad see...twitter thing works and if we were getting the right kind
of feedback actually a lot of things that we haven't done in the past.
Because rethought...the interaction might not work we get too many too much feedback people just
telling us to product...something like that so we,
you know, we still get that feedback but, actually it turns out a ton of people are out there really passion they
want the party better and they give us really amazing honest feedback so,
these are the kinds of things these...of attendance that we held close as we approach the...rebuilding.
These are things that we're going to keep with us as we
...product will be the product we ship the summer with windows ten and then
would improve the product over time with these sort of principles of mine so coming back to?
What we're...actually shipping this summer we decided to focus on?
Three sort of core areas in the products aside from sort of core...the products in the
way reengineering...areas we decide we want to try to put a stake in the ground and do something
different and differentiating with the first-round core...
visual assistant that's built into windows ten comes from windows phone we decide really
think about how we could improve browsing with this idea that I have a personal system that
...sort of help me accomplish the tasks them doing on the web the second is around reading a
...the most common activities that we're doing on the web probably the single all reading,
reading lots of things that people are reading long form the really short form?
They're doing a lot of consumption of content on the web as we decided we're going to try to make that better
as we have a couple features that we've done this released and we're going to do more and more time to really
try to nail that course scenario of people reading on the web and the third thing is around
note-taking so we've seen this idea of people annotating mean creation sharing
this idea of doing research on the web this is something we seen over and over again as a core pattern
of what people are doing on the web...as the integrated the web since their lives and sort of becomes
...part of what they do and we said we're going to try to do some things in that space
really make that easier you'll see some of this the work that we've done in our first
released this summer and will do more and more of that over time so we do a quick demo what we've done?
Ok, so, here we are and I'm going...startup.
Is almost said project...are microsoft edge I will say that at least ten times
directly has been a long-time of not saying microsoft edge?
The start with this is the new tab page that we serve announced this morning.
And, it actually from this you can sort of see the overall how we design the browser the browser
...to sort of focus you on the task that matter
...streamline with minimize the lines that are in the user experience with you know,
move things to where they sort of...should be tabs above
...is a place...we wanted to do for a while sort of reduce the amount of
space used up by the browser chrome so we put your focus on the content
...tab page explicitly something we are spent quite a bit of time integrating on...new tab pages for the
home page are an interesting sort of point in how people use when they use the browser you
started tab because you have something in mind or you want to explore
something we're really nail those core tasks the people are cut want to accomplish they want to go to particular site they want
to do a search...to go to some of the size of the been
...in the past we know from research that people tend to goats' between six and twelve
...over and over and over again so we want to really
...from making sure that we would bring those sites you so that
over time this top site list we can optimize itself to you and the sites that
you go to so that...you just click on your tab go to the site that you wanted to go
to below that we wanted to really create this
personalized experience where we could showcase some apps that you might be interested in
some content the interested in if...the sports teams that you're interested in
...the content will show up here and adapt to that sports teams the stocks
the types of new the different topics that are just you so all these things are this
the content below here is highly personalized to-you and the type of information that you consider valuable.
And, this entire surface is actually designed as a surface that we can iterate and
experiment...so we have the ability over time
to as see things are working if people are accomplishing the task they need to we can
flight different designs and see if it's really meeting the goals that we had that people are able to get
the task they want to accomplish or discover interesting things to them.
So, as I mentioned core...as an important part of india experience that we've
belts and we thought about core...we thought about the difference are ways that she could sort
of help in the...core experiences the browser so one of the most fundamental
...browsers typing the address or doing a search and,...demo this one before
and...about you know, so, you...as you're typing the address...the idea is
core...sort of watching what you're doing you have this personal...kind of watching you're typing and using that
context figure out what it is you might be trying to get too and then bring that
to immediately so that you don't need to go somewhere else so we've shown this
...stuff access couple days ago rolled out a few more
...enhance things including what I have to say is by far my favorite.
This is armistice space there.
Yeah, so,
this is very important I have my ability to tell how brad pitt is a tips my fingers and for those of
you nomads really very important by the way brad pitt is
...you...has seen the centuries-old is...for bromley wasn't
...kind of scary thought.
I can tell you about tom cruise is well if that's anybody now you already know that you guys already now
...is okay so you say that any other questions you-can type in these are common things that people search for when
...thanksgiving when...this flight landing have flight status
in here movie showtime things like that we can bring these things to you so that you have access and support
...able to figure out and infer what you need...kind of bring those things
too the second area?
We invested in as sort of trying to figure out how she can help you complete task so here
me to go to this restaurant you see...top corner core tunnels...of...she says,
you know, I have hours and directions and
menu information for you and it turns out the section of popular features people you know,
this is...great web...restaurant website...perfectly designed but,
a lot of...not this one our...because we got permission to use this site.
A lot of reston websites actually quite difficult to navigate so if you click on this up here
that...information...
can package all the information about the site so if...can tell you know,
the phone-number some yelp reviews it was into within twenty,
twenty miles of your so it would actually...directions from that locate from where you are to that
...whether it's open right now help you book...on open table things like that
...this experience is something that we are expanding over time we have a think
about forty thousand restaurants in right now we're
...expand over the next few months to majority
restaurants united states and then over time torestaurants around the world and,
then we will also be adding different scenarios and...new scenarios
...talk about towards the end of bringing in this idea that, you know, based on the context of what I'm doing the
browsing make personal cystic...help me find what I'm looking for.
And, the final thing that we sort of have is, you know,
this very simple idea that well I could always ask...what?
About something so I click on south lake union here I don't know where it is it gives me a little map and we have like twenty or
thirty different entities that we support here whether it's if it's a food that is used in
a used free commonly used for eating will have a recipe for
it will have some nutrition information if it's a place we'll have a map if it's a...a movie
...tell you what movies and very important look that up all the time.
So, this is the idea that we had is this idea...have this course...
assistant she's available to help me find out all of my brad pitt related information all times.
Okay,
the second thing that we can work...I said is reading so we started by this idea of a reading
lists reading is an interesting scenario so derives from ...dries from favorites...of
...use favors to just keep track of things they want to read later we had this idea that we would come up with
the reading list you could add things explicitly reading list...more beautiful view of them is organized
in reverse order by the things you put in when you click on can take...the site and, you know,
you can easily remove it and say that I'm done with this with reading this article so it's really
optimize around this idea want to put something away and read it a later time?
When you come to the article the other thing that we did was work on this
to distraction free are reading view which is where we take the contents on the page we have
...heuristics pull out the content the core images are reconstruct the
pages something this formal readable and far more interesting to you instead of the distractions
...might be on the page so this is sort of the first couple things we've done around reading
level feedback on them and then we'll work on more in the future
so the second a third thing we did is run annotations there's going to show
you very quickly invites apple the annotation button I can sort of say?
You know.
Right so this is something I can do I can write...directly on the page and then I can sort of
clip this and I don't know brad pitts suing over on the side there
...let-me know...reminded me of brad is never far from my mind?
And, expect this if you.
I can clip this that I can share with my wife ...you have...moi.
See will never see this.
...clip this...share this image and I can make annotations is very,
... we've seen this logical use...scenario different ways they see something on amazon they want a annotated
...send it to somebody and it's not just...you can user finger also have
a if you have a touch-screen you could out you can you attacks annotation as well.
you know, you can share this as well so I'm...quit out of that and hope it was deleted okay, so,
that's the core features core...reading annotation these are
sort of three areas that we try to create some interesting and differentiating scenarios around and, really you know,
try the product and let us know...think ...switch back to.
So, in addition to that.
We want to talk about what microsoft edge is as an app it's built for
windows ten and we'll talk about why that's important why that's interesting is built
...universal windows platform which allows us to actually work across all of these devices over time
we have to design different you why because that is part of which want to do is make sure the core of the app
...goes across for devices but you created a user experiences tailored for each device and,
it's updated frequently along with windows ten is also ready for the future and that senses I
mention briefly before it does also mean that we've left behind some
of the technologies that kind of brabeen part of the ideal history
...this point active-x controls aren't supported and we do support flashing
...natively as part of project spartan but,
active-x is not supported tool bar's ba chose variety of technologies like that which...no longer sport
...script are supported anymore so...a long...list?
You must not working...
So, for our friends and...who do have a large a lot of line-of-business applications
ado requires technologies ie eleven mostly untouched redone course
...work on it is part of the product and...you as
a it administrator will be able to deploy you know, the ...list so that you
either, you know, you actually deploy eleven as the default if that's works for your environment because you have
that many systems that require or you can access or periodically, you know,
launch over to ...explore,
for example, we at work we still have...app the requires some active-x controls so whenever I go to the
expense up it pops out and ie I do the expenses and I close and I go back into microsoft edge.
And, also we take advantage of a lot of security features
...sixty four-bit by default which is something we actually been trying to do for a long-time
actually been held back because most extensibility has been three two-bit up...point and,
we use app containers which is a...technology for as
part of windows ten so these are some of the things that we're sort of built on answer
...grad for windows ten now one of the things you might be sort of wondering
is will windows ten were all these, you know, down level
platforms so as you heard this morning one of our goals is to make sure that windows
...as may devices possible over the past couple years we've upgraded six
hundred fifty million windows seven pc's to spone to get the ready for that
operate windows ten we've upgraded to hundred-million plus windows ax
...to the latest us update of windows eight-point one to get the ready for that
windows...upgrade we have all windows phone devices we have xbox devices and we have new
pc's that we coming out over the next
year the running windows ten so this number sounds a little large.
But, there's a real active plan in place to try to try to get
as many existing users on to windows ten and,
all the different devices the different ...on with ten so...the you the based on which microsoft
edge will be running will actually be huge in a very short amount of time and,
this course is the default browser on the desktop...of browser on
peat on the phone as well and it's available on the other devices that we've talked about so that's a bit
about the app hanover talk a little bit about html...pictures of.
So, yeah,
I mean I'll start out again by apologizing advances going to be a sharp
decrease in brad pitt related content for the next little while sorry.
...so, that's good for some people apparently.
So, I'm going to talk about microsoft edge html which is the new rendering engine that
powers microsoft edge so I talked a little bit earlier about
some of the broad trends that we were seeing across web what we were hearing from
our customers and what we ended up doing last may actually was we?
Formed are platform priorities and we really rallied around this single statement that we
published on our blog last may and statement was really simple the web should
just work for everyone users developers and businesses
and this was a reflection of what we were hearing and seeing from people was that this kind of fundamental promise
of the web wasn't actually working as promised so let me show you a quick example of what we're seeing.
So, in general, you know, this is the web that were used to right you've got
...works great works the same across a bunch
of different browsers and this is the web that you know, that this is what the web promises.
So, we're good write.
Well, actually it turns out that we weren't seeing that all
over the place on an increasing number of sites we
started to see situations more like this especially where the sites were adopting
more modern technologies things that were perhaps only available in one browser so this
is very prevalent on the mobile web so you had a certain browser that was,
you know,
through no-fault...for through no fault of its own actually racing ahead providing new capabilities to
developers providing the market share and developers were getting excited in building
...for it so this was kind of, you know, harking back to the isis days and
although pushes the web forward it also takes away from some that
...diversity that I talked about earlier that's really the fundamental value of the web so
we really wanted to bring that tenet of the web just works back to the modern web.
So, we were faced with kind of this question of how do we start to push forward and fix a lot
of these interoperability issues that we were seeing that were causing these things on
the modern web as well as continuing to make our customers
happy that had a lot of dependencies on ie proprietary technology and just one
of those sites written in the year two thousand so to just keep on working.
And, that's what led us to not just a break from
the past but a fork from the past so we actually
forks the ie engine microsoft html and created a new engine that were calling at
And, the reason we did that was to really free ourselves
from the compatibility burden so we can now leave that engine in
place for compatibility and we now have this new engine that could be hundred-percent focused on
interoperability so let's take a look at how that works so this was kind of the old story in I we had
the one engine.
And, we said hey we're going to deliver everything in this one place we're going to deliver the latest
html five standard and by the way that site you wrote that requires
phoebe script and active-x and all that other stuff is going to continue to work.
part of the way we did that was by implementing...we call document mods so
...been out for many years and I still run across people who have been developed developing for
...and still don't quite understand them and it turned out they were they were pretty confusing
because you had one browser that can now behave in a bunch of different ways depending on what...it was in.
And, again, we try to say hey uses browser whether you're browsing the latest html five
sight or on your internet a or enterprise mode site.
So, now with forking the engine what we were able to do is
take that engine and give it a really clear purpose.
So, now in windows ten microsoft html has a very clear purposes, purposes to be
backwards compatible in fact since we're not really touching it other than security fixes as
...mentioned we can now tell our customers with much higher degree of confidence that this
thing's going to continue to work as it did before so continues
to support the same technologies as it always does always did
but now has a very focused
purpose for mostly for enterprise and internet sites as well
certain regions around the world like korea that have a big dependency on active-x.
And, allows us to introduces new browser new rendering
engine say for the vast majority of users that don't have a dependency on
all these technologies then here's the browser we expect like I said the vast
majority of windows ten users to be on microsoft edge so once we made that split it really
...to start piling a bunch of interoperability improvements ripping out all
of that ie specific stuff and fixing a lot of the differences
are gaps between microsoft edge in other modern browsers.
In fact.
In microsoft edge...over forty two hundred
...ability improvements on top of
I eleven and as you can see.
They're still they're still trickling in as we speak.
the animation as waiting for this is actually hooked up directly into our source code system and.
how do we know that this is actually working so I took you through the scenario before?
...different experience across different devices now with edge you actually see
the same the same experience is a combination of a
new user agent string of course but also interoperability improvements so that we
...same there's no doubt no changes required from the website in this case.
But, of course we can't just say here's one or two or three or
...ten-hour hundred sites that are now better we need to look
...that the web is forty-some billion web
websites.
So, this is where we can really leverage the telemetry that I talked about earlier so I
...through the smiley face and how it's really important for us to be able to
enable people to give us feedback within just a couple clicks so here's an example of how
we're using that feedback so this is telemetry that showing
us how the number of reports that we get between the old engine and then you...so there
...a period of time over the last few months where they were both out there and actually if
you installed windows ten you didn't know what engine you were going to get we actually had
basically ab testing happening and you could go
...override if you wanted to but for the vast majority of our users they didn't know necessarily they were getting
a new engine and what's not allowed us to do was compare the amount of feedback we were
getting between each and tell us if we were doing better than the
old engine and what you see here towards the left is that when we first released
...new engine this is back in november we were actually doing worse and this
...expected because we change the user agent string we got rid of all the
ie specific tokens...we're really serious about rendering the same content
is other browsers and yet so we're getting content that had no
...specific work-arounds or anything and things are breaking because we didn't have
all the interoperability fixes in yet and yet as you move towards the right you can see that as we release new
...things start to get better and better and crossing over that dotted line was the point where
we a few weeks ago start to see more positive feedback
or I guess we could say less negative feedback for the new browser than we did for the
for the old one and of course we're just going to continue fixing continue,
continue checking in those...improvement so this is just going to continue going up?
So, I talk a bunch about interoperability and making them web
...work but of course we also want to push the leading edge of the web
content pun sort of intended I guess leading edge of the web forward.
So, we implemented a whole bunch of new features so this is a list directly
...status dot...you can always get the latest list here of
...so, this forty five so standards
that are coming in development or in preview today in microsoft edge.
So, that's all the time
have to cover right now on the platform there's a lot more detail to
come actually feel kinda bad for not showing you any code in a platform session but
thankfully there's a lot coming in the session so actually it's going to start tomorrow in the keynote
when david tread well and kevin gallagher going to give a demo of a new cite site
arcade that combines a bunch of these new technologies together you also see some great
...improvements that I had to try really hard not to
tell you about today so that they can you can be surprised tomorrow as well as more about hosted web
article talk about in a second?
Next up you've got making your site rock with
...twelve this actually happened a couple of hours ago so hopefully you caught it
...not then you can see...talk online so
...the rtwelve tools if you're familiar with them with ieee those are coming,
coming over to microsoft edge and new improved version of
...twelve will be the developer tooling for microsoft edge then we've got on friday we've got a couple
of sessions both of them will be super technical first rendering engine
deep dive with david and david and, you know,
lots of code lots of demos create session and then finally brian
we'll be talking about building a fasten scalable apps with javascript
so on the previous slide you probably notice that there's a whole lot of ecma
script six features on the slide so really happy that
microsoft edge actually currently has the leading implementation of the next generation of
javascript...
As measured by third-party site.
So, if you're interested in learning more about
that definitely check out brian's talk it's super technical
also if you're if you're javascript coder and you want to geek out definitely don't miss that.
All right so now we've got to move on to the third aspect which is web apps
new about platform for windows ten.
So, as I mentioned earlier web apps in general are big trend and
we've really we've had a number of ways to include the web and apps over the
past few releases so we've had things like hybrid apps web you controls as
well as packaged apps where you could use html and write a bunch of code on the client.
Instead of using example let's say in csharp but we felt like we really needed
a new approach and the reason for this is really,
really comes down to what terry talked about this morning in the keynote and that's
really about providing a more natural bridge from the way all of these
different platforms work into the universal windows platform so really providing
...for people to bring their apps to windows in a more natural way.
So, today I'm going to talk about give you a few more details about what that means for the web so what
we're enabling that's new is what we call hosted web apps...I...talk just a little bit
about how this is different from the other web app approaches we've delivered in the past.
So, the first is that your website is really the foundation for your
store app and what this means is that it's literally a url
...put into a manifest and that gets published the store you don't have to download your side and
...up locally you don't even have to put a web view control into your app this is
not just about just a website wrapper?
what really makes it not just a website wrapper is that you can augment
the experience I said your...is the foundation and the reason
is just the foundation is that you can now augment your site experience
using the universal windows api so if there's anything that you need in the
...in the windows api so let's say access to a device that's not part
of the standards-based web platform you can now do that through the
through javascript in the windows universal windows api?
And, the best part of this is that there's no change
...web workflow so again you might be thinking we've done this in the past, you know,
I have a web control and I know how to call from that out into local package
...my app that is not would hosted web apps is all about it's really about
having no change your web workload that means that the javascript code this call
and the universal windows api is actually living on your server so when you need to deploy
an update to that code you just do the same workflow that you always
do hit deploy and all of your users...immediately updated.
So, here's how could look in practice so here's an example of a simple
website sample website that we've created so it's...it's
...responsive website travel app and
its functional as a website you can do to the basic scenarios here.
However, we'd like to lighted up we'd like to
augmented when it's installed as a hosted web app on windows ten.
So, what we can do is just feature detect windows so in the
same way that on the web...feature detect anyhtml five feature
in javascript let's say because you're not sure if the browser that is hitting you is going to support
it you feature detect windows again this code is living on your server so
...say if windows then we can now call a windows specific api?
And, once if your site is running in a...app context
then all of...your travel...augmented and start and put a
calendar appointment directly into the users calendar so you can imagine if it's running as a
website and you can use don't do this or you make them download and I cs file or
something like that so this is a great example of augmenting the experience making sure they get
a better more native feeling experience when they're your site is...app.
So, again, the great thing about this is that you can deploy this code you
can updates code immediately without having to go through any kind of app store approval process.
So, in addition to hosted web apps for also improving other types of web app
so again we know peopleuse more of a hybrid model where they've got a web you control
also there's much improved way to call between
...coding your control as well as coding your app using the ad web
allowed objects so no more invoke script a sinking all that as well as some new api
eyes and package web apps are getting a lot better one of the biggest
kernels that we heard about that was the security restrictions so that's going to get a lot better
using the content security policy or csp the standard which allow you to
basically white list domains that you want your app to be able to communicate with.
So,...lot more their thank you get you get the message if you want to learn more about
...apps then please check out jeff and carol session tomorrow at eleven thirty
am where though go into a more detail and have a lot of demos encode?
So, what we talked about as I mentioned earlier this is we
really thinking about microsoft edge as something the revolving overtime...shown you talked about
...stuff we're doing for our team released this summer we actually,
you know,...you a service...to things that are coming after that kinda get you an idea of what we're focused on
so the first actually was important that you should do is actually spent some time on status...modern
...ieee...new url that will becoming you can redirect from there they'll
get really this idea of what standards are coming into some really interesting standards like
object rtc which is the next step of web rtc allowing
...peer-to-peer communication between browsers soundscape scenarios,
for example, and, poynter...which is really interesting one for gaming where you can
lock the mouse pointer to the browser so that people can do first-person shooters,
for example, so, these are...standards that are coming ...our tm and
...keep track of how those are coming we'll have a previews that you can sort of see how these working
after team the other thing that I'll just do a quick demo of
...take some questions is extensions now this morning you saw?
Geo talk about.
Talk about extensions now...to make clear is x these extensions the work the surveys is
a early code and will actually not be ready for...not...to have this extensibility
...will come after or xhtml have previous people start working with
after-hour tm and get a sense of over building but just give you a sense of that,
you know,...you a couple demos one is the red example
where we basically tookexisting extension built by the read enhancements
...and open-source team...a group of engineers who just wanted to
ads and features the reddit site the reddit and ceo of reddit one point said it was the, you know,
I love you guys actually it's
...it's actually pretty interesting symbiotic relationship when talks these guys and we
...got their code and we basically took that and we were able to bring it over to microsoft
edge almost unchanged so they basically has all the core functionality if you're
ready user allow this functionality is you very familiar to you including things like
the image preview inline previous that we have any click-through to the...of other features that
...through ads and all those features are actually brought online without any changes
any material changes from the original developer and
...with the pinterest example that we showed no,
this is the pinterest extension and, we actually again...for the pinterest and we got
their code and we were able to bring it up with a very few changes to the to the to
the extension itself so we're actually trying to support these html
five javascript extensions that are sort of the standard on the web today and make it really,
really easy to have extension today to bring over to project spartan one essentially
he didn't show was...was some work that we actually did with our?
Being translating where they wrote an extension for us that also happens...browsers.
Eating this looks like an interesting site and you see the top in the address
...the pool icons as I can translate this side as well but...also have this reading view features so with
a little bit of extra work this...take advantage of the fact...a review features well
the one I click reading view actual actually...and translate
automatically the same time so I get this distraction free and actually readable for me
sit on speak spanish version of this site so, you know, that's kind of what happened there is a
detected unreviewed automatically translated that and that was something...kind of
...we'd like to actually do with extensions as a
...online as is have them do unique stuff with the features that we have in the browsers we're going to
make those things available for extension developers we have a few more we have a great
...the...team to enhance the phone numbers on the page and,
then one of illogical favorites turn off the lights...you go to video
...stables recent makes everything dim except the video digital we found it very easy
to take the extensions from different developers kind of standing up in the browser so this is early work and
...will becoming after...have a lot more information on the blogs for people to look into but just, you know,
...give people, you know, linus...were coming at any work
...sort of exist today with other browsers we'll bring that work over and actually then you'll be able to
lighted up on spartan with new features.
The other thing that you'll see is we're going to bring in more
...features a few months ago we had the weather and...scenario will be brought
online the very important brad pitt age scenario and, you know, we have reference
...movies flight times...text supports a very common thing that people searches like,
you know, this thing craswell actually have scenarios...tonic...can help with getting on the right track with
text support so all these things will becoming online between now and our...and
then over time after that we...some interesting scenarios like the shopping scenario that
we're bringing online around you go to a shopping site and we offer some coupons that might be available
...all these things the way we've designed the products essential very
early on with people expect...smarter and more person we've designed is a lot of these features can
...let up purely with server-side changes so that we can
adapt to the different kinds of snares that people use we can adapt to you know,
what's been successful with not being successful and sort of make a better browser over
time so the more people use it...more we can figure out what people need?
...just you back.
All right so, you know, as I started out by saying we started about a year-ago with
this fundamental notion that we need to have a closer connection with developers
and enthusiast basically all of you and that's not something that's going to stop so I
...to just leave with...thought of please, you know,...treat microsoft edge in the platform
...what platform as kind of this community thing and we want to make sure that
it's more building what's what you
want as a user as a developer so there's a bunch of resources here user voice
status site that we talked about a lot of these urls are going to change in the very near future because of the
...but, as sean said don't worry they're they will continue to
...they will redirect to the right to the new homes
also very active on twitter at ie dep chat which is also going to
change the to add microsoft edge dev at any time now as well as
...overflow and we're putting more and more of our samples and things
on get hub the last thing I want to leave you with is if you want to know even more
so I pointed at you at a bunch of scenario sessions here to learn more but
next week we're actually having a full two-day event in mountain view just down the highway
we're calling the microsoft edge web some it so this is going-to be to
full two-day event all about microsoft edge really focused at developers so,
for today it was actually it's very close sold out we actually decided to
open up registration again today just for build to make sure that people who wanted to come can make it
and if you're in town or can stick around a little bit longer definitely go to aka
...dot microsoft slash microsoft edge some it and you can register for free?
So, with that thank you very much once again please please fill
...evaluation and I think we've got a few minutes for questions
...the session yes so you probably google...can stay for hours for
question so if you've got a question please step up to one of the mikes so,
everyone can hear thanks...thank you.
On...got a question over here so with the we've been taking my
website and making, making into a web app is you mentioned...urls spaces and
it goes into the store yet doesn't have to go into the store can I deploy that
within the enterprise without having...still get all those
benefits within the enterprise you can deploy it because I believe
we've got an enterprise store story so you can basically have a private
Yet but for broad...does have to go through the store okay thank you thanks.
So, for the mark-up where you're in the browser in your making your annotations
...where's all that stored is...pushed up into...your cloud
or how do we share that across devices so right now the what happens is
...store locally and then you can shared...a package we rendered out as
...html file with...the...intractable you
...share that file put it on your cloud overtime we'd like to have more seamless ways but on the
cloud automatically for-you things like that but it's pretty package you can
just share another person gets it gets it as you saw it sort of
frozen in time with your annotations and your comments are available on it
...thanks in just obviously would be great if that was just kind of universal
...if I brought up the web page on my desktop I would see my...crazy back thank you?
Hi, maybe you've already mentioned this and I missed it but what is your
release strategy after the big launch this summer is it rolling releases every thirty days
are you locks to the next version of windows it whenever you feel like it?
It's sort of so,
being...next version of windows enrolling releases are actually now the same thing
that's where the big changes are happen with windows ten is a windows
ten itself will actually be doing rolling releases and consumers...sort of brought along
and this is one of the big sort of pushes of windows...platform broadly is that and the entire
...up for windows...is going to be kept evergreen across the entire consumer base and,
broad...edge with the platform will move along with that so we actually can update on
a regular cadencewe haven't quite worked out the exact like is
it going to be forty five days or ninety days or seventy three days or anything like that we haven't quite worked out
...but, we have the technical ability to sort
of updates are bring the entire user base along with us
at a rapid pace so rolling updates evergreen browser that is the
plan that we have...one thing I'll add real quick is that, you know,
the insider program is as we've
...going to continue after-hour tm and
...has very little bit but lately we've really we've really
aim for twice a month for so-if you want really the latest and greatest that's the way
to get the get the latest and greatest opted twice a month
...really two weeks basis in terms of how often we want to push
those bits out to kind of the rest of our customers we're still figuring that out of...said.
Thanks.
There was somebody there.
Is a free...over...well the weather...available...all of the platforms that windows
ten supports the...xbox and holdings?
Yes, absolutely yet so they're going to go into the universal store.
the question was will the web apps be available...all windows ten platforms and the
answer's yes so especially if you have a great responsive web experience
that's that scales across those different form factors and your...basically got a great
headstart on a on app across all those devices so the only tradeoffs with
that compared to like an native universe...might be some of the specific functionality like
...tiles and other things like that right, yeah, but,
actually with access to the universal windows api you can actually light up a lot of those
that functionality now from your web app.
What I'm that's...so I have two questions first one I know...
it's a longer line but I apologize
...first one with the it being able
roll-out I a and setting that is amended is there
any statement about being able to end-of-life and ie
...when medal the?
We haven't made any statements
...guidance and we're working with customers definitely to help
them migrate off of those technologies but we haven't set a marker in the future that's definitely the
direction we're moving but we want to provided transition time to our customers to get off a
lot of these all technologies we don't know exactly how long that's going to take at this point
here so second question about the web apps is what about certification
because if they're going into the store is there any sort of certification,
yeah, that you have to go through and how does that work with doing updates and things like that, yeah, so,
you'll be certified the first-time you go through just like any other update because
subsequent updates basicallycircumvent the normal kind of packaged
app review process that obviously doesn't work so we have a separate process
...place where both just through kind of regular reviews of
existing apps as well as of course monitoring feedback...and app gets a bunch of
complains, for example,...we have a team of folks that will kind of regularly?
Review apps...as there in-flight so to speak so if we
...a bunch complaints and of course will take action and pull it down or do whatever?
Okay, so, I think we're done with sort of the recorded
questions come up here ask questions will be here thank you very much thank you.